Inventory of the E. B. Brossard papers
Hoover Institution Archives
E. B. Brossard papers
1908-2007
2001C91
Hoover Institution Archives
57 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (23.2 linear feet)
The papers consist primarily of Brossard's writings and research materials, the bulk of which pertain to the history of the Venezuelan oil industry and to modern Venezuelan politics. In addition, the papers contain a considerable quantity of research materials relating to the general history of the international petroleum industry. The research materials are comprised largely of reports, serial issues, and clippings, and are grouped by subject. The papers include some correspondence relating both to Brossard's research and to her career as a professor of political science at a number of American universities.
Brossard, E. B.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1928 Born, San Juan, Puerto Rico
1940 Bachelor of Arts, University of Wisconsin at Madison
1971 Doctorate in political science, Claremont College
1983 Author, Petroleum: Politics and Power
1993 Author, Petroleum Research and Venezuela's INTEVEP: The Clash of the Titans
2001 Author, Power and Petroleum: Venezuela, Cuba and Colombia, a Troika?
1973-1975 Taught at Hillsdale College, Michigan
1975-1982 Visiting professor and then associate professor of government, University of West Florida, Pensacola
1982-1991 Associate professor of government, Louisiana State University at Baton Rouge
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist primarily of Brossard's writings and research materials, the bulk of which pertain to the history of the Venezuelan oil industry and to modern Venezuelan politics. In addition, the papers contain a considerable quantity of research materials relating to the general history of the international petroleum industry. The research materials are comprised largely of reports, serial issues, and clippings, and are grouped by subject. The papers include some correspondence relating both to Brossard's research and to her career as a professor of political science at a number of American universities.
Emma Brossard derived her knowledge of Venezuela from personal experience -- she spent part of her childhood there -- and from her study of the country's politics and oil industry. She wrote her doctoral dissertation on Rómulo Betancourt, president of Venezuela from 1945 to 1948 and again from 1959 to 1964. Brossard went on to write numerous articles and several monographs on the Venezuelan oil industry. In her last years, Brossard was a fierce critic of former Venezuelan president Hugo Chávez, and the papers contain her articles and research materials on Chávez.
The papers contain extensive documentation on the activities of Petróleos de Venezuela, the country's national oil company, as well as those of its many subsidiaries. These materials include annual reports, financial statements, statistics, and articles from the Venezuelan press. There are also papers from a number of conferences held on the subject of the Venezuelan oil industry. As a whole, the materials trace the history of the Venezuelan oil industry from its beginnings down to the Chávez era.
A significant portion of the papers concern Brossard's teaching career at Louisiana State University, Hillsdale College, and the University of West Florida. These materials include her correspondence with academic officials and students, speeches and addresses made by Brossard, and course materials from classes she taught.
There are some sound and video recordings in the papers, including an audio interview of Rómulo Betancourt conducted by Brossard in 1970 (box 1). The papers also contain the first volume of Emma Brossard's unpublished memoirs (box 40), as well as articles and papers relating to one of Brossard's former teachers, the political philosopher Leo Strauss (boxes 9, 49, and 53).
Petroleum industry and trade.; Petroleum industry and trade--Venezuela.; Venezuela--Politics and government.; Betancourt, Rómulo, 1908-1981.; Petróleos de Venezuela, S.A.
- Betancourt, Rómulo, 1958-1976
  - Two sound cassettes containing an interview of Betancourt conducted by Brossard, Caracas, Venezuela, 1970 September 23 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
  - Agrarian reform under Betancourt's administration, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - International democratic solidarity meeting, 1976 May (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Visit by Richard Nixon to Venezuela, 1958 May (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Articles by and about Betancourt, 1958-1976
    - 1958-1970 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1971-1976 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Correspondence between Brossard and Betancourt, 1968-1974 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Writings by Brossard, 1966-1994
  - Master's thesis, "The Military Government of Marcos Pérez Jiménez,", 1966 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Doctoral dissertation, "Rómulo Betancourt: A Study in the Evolution of a Constitutional Statesman,", 1970 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "LOOP: Engineering Marvel, Economic Calamity,", 1985 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Foreward to compilation of documents relating to Simón Bolívar, 1984 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "Brossard's Iron Mountain,", 1984 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Articles written for Wall Street Journal, 1980-1994 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "Rómulo Betancourt, Father of OPEC,", 1979 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "Rómulo Betancourt y Fidel Castro,", 1975 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Testimony given by Brossard to Ways and Means Committee, Louisiana Legislature, 1986 October 29 (Box-folder 2: 7)
- "Venezuela and the Oil Pioneers," edited by Brossard, 1958-1991 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Betancourt, Rómulo, 1981 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Writings by Brossard, 1983-1991
  - Articles written for Oil Daily, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - White papers published by Louisiana State University, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Articles written for Center for Energy Studies, Louisiana State University, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Testimony given by Brossard before Congressional committees, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Correspondence, 1980-1999
  - Venezuelan graduate students, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - General, 1988-1999
    - 1988-1991 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1992-1994 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1995-1999 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Institute for the Study of Earth and Man, Southern Methodist University, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - General, 1980-1987
    - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1985-1987 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Centro de formación y adiestramiento de Petróleos de Venezuela, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Subroto, Dr., 1989-1996 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Fernández Morán, Humberto, 1983-1998 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Hedberg, Hollis D., 1981-1996 (Box-folder 6: 4)
- Lousiana State University, 1980-1987
  - Industry meetings, 1982-1986 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Articles and speeches by Brossard, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Paper by Brossard, 1986 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Oklahoma energy conference, 1985 (Box-folder 7: 4)
  - "The Oil Traders and the International Oil Market," conference paper, Copenhagen, Denmark, 1985 October 15 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - "Refining Oil Abroad: The Political and Economic Costs," conference paper, Fort Lauderdale, Florida, 1984 November 27 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Delta Assembly, 1984 November (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - Correspondence on Natural Gas Act, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Trip to Costa Rica, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Testimony on energy security, 1984 August 30 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Responses to book and articles by Brossard, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Center for Energy Studies, 1982-1985 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - International oil conference, 1983 September (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Articles by Brossard, 1983 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - "Save El Salvador - The Venezuelan Way,", 1983 October (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Perspectives speakers series, 1982 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Testimony on natural gas, 1982 October 1 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Letters to administrators, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 7: 18)
- Claremont Graduate University, term papers and correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 7: 19)
- Hillsdale College, 1973-1986
  - General correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Letters from Hillsdale students, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Conference on federal health insurance, 1975 April (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Jaffa, Harry, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - Joeghen, Raymond de, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Commencement address, 1973 May 19 (Box-folder 8: 6)
- Earhart Foundation, 1974-1980 (Box-folder 8: 7)
- University of West Florida, 1975-1982
  - "OPEC and the Dollar," conference paper, 1979 November 13 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - "Energy in the Southern Triangle,", 1979 October (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Distinguished teaching award, 1979 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - "Coming-Blackouts,", 1978 October 11 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - "The Sea Lanes around South Africa," conference papers, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Televised talk on natural gas, 1978 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Speeches and classes, 1975-1982 (Box-folder 8: 15)
  - Papers by students, 1976-1982 (Box-folder 8: 16)
- American Security Council seminar, 1979 April (Box-folder 9: 1)
- International Conference on Alternative Energy Sources, Miami, Florida, 1987 December 14-16 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Orinoco oil belt proposal, 1981 (Box-folder 9: 3)
- Conoco Energy Forum, 1981 November 2-4 (Box-folder 9: 4)
- International Conference on Heavy Crude and Tar Sands, Caracas, Venezuela, 1982 February 7-17 (Box-folder 9: 5)
- St. Norbert College, 1970-1986
  - "Founding a Government and Trying to Keep It,", 1973 October 13 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Congressional sessions, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Clippings, 1972 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Students, 1973-1986 (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Paper on Plato and article on Leo Strauss, 1974-1985 (Box-folder 9: 11)
- Hillsdale College, 1973-1975
  - Imprimis, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - "Affirmative Action - Who Is Wrong?," speech, 1974 December 5 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Washington-Hillsdale Intern Program, 1975 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Arboretum, 1973 (Box-folder 9: 15)
- Conferences, 1985-1997
  - Task force on natural gas, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - International Research Center for Energy and Economic Development conferences, 1989-1997 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Institute for the Study of Earth and Man conference, Dallas, Texas, 1987 October 1-2 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - Central American Conference on Trade, Investment and Development, Tegucigalpa, Honduras, 1987 March 12-14 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Joint Conference on a Pan American Energy Alliance, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1987 April 2-4 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Natural Gas Fair, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, 1987 May (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Louisiana Economic Summit, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, 1986 May 19 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - International oil markets conference, Baton Rouge, Louisiana, 1986 April 4 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Louisiana Energy Development Study Commission session, 1986 March 25 (Box-folder 10: 9)
- Thompson, A. Beeby, The Oilfields of Russia and the Russian Petroleum Industry, 1908 (Box-folder 10: 10)
- Monographs by Brossard, 1975-1993
  - Petroleum: Politics and Power (1983)
    - Evaluations, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Letters from readers, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - Comments and corrections, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - Correspondence with publishers, 1976-1984 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - Notices in catalogs, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - Houston trip, 1976 March (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - OPEC trip, 1975 October (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Petroleum Research and Venezuela's INTEVEP: The Clash of the Titans (1993)
    - Spanish edition, 1985 (Box-folder 11: 8-9)
    - Letters of acknowledgment, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 10)
    - Photos and inserts, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 11)
    - Pictures, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 12)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 11: 13-14)
    - Subroto, Dr., 1989-1993 (Box-folder 11: 15)
    - Contract, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 16)
- Working trips to Venezuela, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- Curriculum vitae, 1975-1983 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Proposals for Argentina, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 12: 3-4)
- Writings by Brossard, 1988-2000
  - "Overseas Oil Investments," Petroleum Management, 1988 February/March (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - "ANWR and the Imperial Congress," Houston Geological Society Bulletin, 1988 April (Box-folder 12: 6)
  - "The SPR, Convenient Gore Campaign Ploy,", 2000 September 23 (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Correspondence, 1991-2000
  - Thunderbird Executive Training Center, 1991 (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - García Laredo, Victor, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Weekly Standard, 2000 (Box-folder 12: 10)
- Paper by Edward L. Morse, 1991 (Box-folder 12: 11)
- Rice University, 1993 (Box-folder 12: 12)
- Articles about Brossard, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 12: 13-14)
- Album of photographs depicting oil refineries, Venezuela, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 1)
- Venezuelan oil industry lobbying program, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 13: 2)
- Registration as foreign agent, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13: 3)
- Official visit to Chile, 1984 April (Box-folder 13: 4)
- Venezuela, 1985-1995
  - "Venezuela's Role in World Oil Supplies: Past, Present, and Future," conference, Washington, D.C., 1985 September 13 (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 1985-1995
    - Correspondence, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
    - Monthly reports, 1985-1995
      - 1985-1988 (Box-folder 14: 3)
      - 1989-1990 (Box-folder 14: 4)
      - 1991-1992 (Box-folder 15: 1)
      - 1993-1995 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Trip by company delegation to Louisiana, 1989 (Box-folder 15: 3)
- Southwest Energy Council, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 15: 4)
- Speeches and writings by Brossard, 1988-1998
  - Notes for lecture on Venezuelan oil industry, Rice University, 1988 October (Box-folder 15: 5)
  - "What Is OPEC in 1990?,", 1989 October (Box-folder 15: 6)
  - "The Global Energy Picture and OPEC," speech, Lake Conroe, Texas, 1989 October 21 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - "OPEC's Natural Gas," speech at Enron seminar, Houston, Texas, 1989 November 15 (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - "OPEC's Gas," speech, 1990 April (Box-folder 15: 9)
  - Review of book by Laura Randall, 1994 (Box-folder 15: 10)
  - "Naysayers Wrong about Orimulsion," Palm Beach Post, 1998 June 23 (Box-folder 15: 11)
- Report on Venezuelan debt, 1985 (Box-folder 16: 1)
- Interview with Brossard, 2001 (Box-folder 16: 2)
- Tchourilov, Lev, Russia's Petroleum, 1995 (Box-folder 16: 3)
- Betancourt, Rómulo, 1958-1978
  - Pamphlets, 1958-1961 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - 50 años de vida política, comprised of 8 sound cassettes and one brochure, 1978 (Box-folder 16: 5)
- Compilations of Daily Journal articles, 1965 (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
- Commemorative issues of El Nacional, 2003 (Box-folder 17: 3-8)
- Conference poster, 1985 (Box-folder 17: 9-10)
- Organización Latinoamericana de Energía, 1984-1999 (Box-folder 18: 1)
- Venezuela, 1926-2001
  - Agricultural agreement, 1984 (Box-folder 18: 2)
  - Background information, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - Petroleum industry chronology, 1970-1991 (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - Bariven, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Centro Inernacional de Educación y Desarrollo, 1989-1999 (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - Coal, 1986 (Box-folder 18: 7)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 1982-2001
    - Deltaven, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 18: 8)
    - Intevep, 1985-2000 (Box-folder 18: 9)
    - PDV Marina, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 18: 10)
    - Intesa, 1997 (Box-folder 18: 11)
    - Palmaven, 1988 (Box-folder 18: 12)
    - Corpoven, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 18: 13)
    - Menever, 1983 (Box-folder 18: 14)
    - Maraven, 1982-1995 (Box-folder 18: 15)
    - Lagoven, 1984-1997 (Box-folder 18: 16)
    - Cryogenic complex, 1984-1998 (Box-folder 18: 17)
    - Cristóbal Colón, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 18: 18)
    - Pequiven, 1990-2001 (Box-folder 18: 19-20)
  - Oil and Gas Journal reports, 1991-2001 (Box-folder 18: 21)
  - Special supplements on Venezuelan economy, 1978-1998 (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - Legal developments, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - Classification for petroleum, 1987 (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - Unitar, 1991 (Box-folder 19: 4)
  - Asphalt, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 19: 5)
  - Crude oil, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 19: 6)
  - La Apertura, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 19: 7)
  - Proyecto Apure, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - El Furrial, 1985-2000 (Box-folder 19: 9)
  - Sisor, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 19: 10)
  - Oil spill contingency plans, 1985-2001 (Box-folder 19: 11)
  - Reformulated gasoline, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 19: 12)
  - Corpovoz articles, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 19: 13)
  - PDVSA al día, 1998-1999
    - 1998 (Box-folder 19: 14)
    - 1999 (Box-folder 19: 15)
  - PDVSA Contact, 1987-2001 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Houston Chronicle, 1996 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - Oil Daily, 1991 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - Speeches and interviews, 1980-1993
    - Vogeler Rincones, Carlos, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 20: 4)
    - Alcock, Frank, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 20: 5)
    - Chacín Guzmán, Juan, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 20: 6)
    - Ravard, Rafael Alonzo, 1980 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 1983-1996 (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - Geological reports, 1926-1940 (Box-folder 20: 9)
- Arab oil embargo, 1973-1983 (Box-folder 20: 10)
- Iranian oil cutoff, 1979-1992 (Box-folder 20: 11)
- Natural gas and OPEC, 1984-1997 (Box-folder 20: 12)
- Organization of Arab Petroleum Exporting Countries, 1977-1995 (Box-folder 21: 1)
- Non-OPEC alliance, 1986-1998 (Box-folder 21: 2)
- Aramco, 1972-1988 (Box-folder 21: 3)
- State oil companies, 1980-1994 (Box-folder 21: 4)
- Venezuela, 1971-2001
  - Arias Cárdenas, Francisco, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 21: 6)
  - Chávez, Hugo, 2001 (Box-folder 21: 7)
  - Elections, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 8)
  - Floods, 1999 (Box-folder 21: 9)
  - Asamblea Nacional Constituyente, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 21: 10)
  - Decree 1011, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 11)
  - Chávez and the Church, 2000 (Box-folder 21: 12)
  - Chávez and Fidel Castro, 2000 (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - Castro's visits to Venezuela, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 22: 2)
  - General news, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 22: 3)
  - Union referendum, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 22: 4)
  - Orimulsion, 1980-1998 (Box-folder 22: 5-6)
  - Monographs, 1971-1993 (Box-folder 23: 1-4)
- Persian Gulf oil, 1975 (Box-folder 23: 5-6)
- Venezuela, 1954-2004
  - History of petroleum industry, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 24: 1-2)
  - Petroleum statistics, 1975-1984 (Box-folder 24: 3-5)
  - Lott, Leo B., "Venezuelan Federalism, A Case Study in Frustration," doctoral thesis, 1954 (Box-folder 24: 6)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 2002-2003
    - 2002 (Box-folder 25: 1-2)
    - 2003 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - Corrales Plan, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 25: 4)
  - Chávez, Hugo, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 25: 5-6)
  - Quirós Corradi, Alberto, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 25: 7)
  - Romero, Evanan, 1974-2002 (Box-folder 25: 8)
  - Monograph by Brossard, Power and Petroleum: Venezuela, Cuba and Colombia, a Troika?, 2001 (Box-folder 25: 9)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 2002 (Box-folder 26: 1-4)
  - March against Chávez, 2002 (Box-folder 27: 1-3)
  - Chávez, Hugo, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 27: 4)
  - Articles by Carlos A. Ball, 1997-2003 (Box-folder 28: 1)
  - Tax treaty with U.S., 1999 (Box-folder 28: 2)
  - Currency crisis, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 28: 3)
  - Debt, 1984-2004 (Box-folder 28: 4-5)
  - Banco Latino collapse, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 28: 6)
  - Guerrillas, 1966-2002 (Box-folder 28: 7)
  - Indians, 1960-2000 (Box-folder 28: 8)
  - Military, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 28: 9)
  - Border dispute with Colombia, 1965-2003 (Box-folder 28: 10)
  - Drug trafficking, 1985-2002 (Box-folder 28: 11)
  - Chávez, Hugo, 1999-2004
    - Trips, 1999 (Box-folder 28: 12)
    - Humor, 1999-2002 (Box-folder 28: 13)
    - Bush, George W., 2004 (Box-folder 28: 14)
    - Organic hydrocarbons law, 2001 (Box-folder 28: 15)
    - Exchange controls, 2003 (Box-folder 28: 16)
    - El Reafirmazo, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 29: 1)
    - General, 1999-2004
      - 1999 (Box-folder 29: 2)
      - 2000 (Box-folder 29: 3)
      - 2003-2004 (Box-folder 29: 4)
  - Monograph, 1999 (Box-folder 30: 1)
  - Elections, 1998 (Box-folder 30: 2)
  - Coup d'état attempt, 1992 (Box-folder 30: 3)
  - Energy reforms, 2002 (Box-folder 30: 4)
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 1996-2004
    - General, 2004 (Box-folder 30: 5)
    - Rodríguez Araque, Alí (Box-folder 30: 6-7)
    - Strike, 2002 (Box-folder 30: 8-10)
    - Parra, Gastón, 2002 (Box-folder 31: 1)
    - Lameda Montero, Guaicaipuro, 2002 (Box-folder 31: 2)
    - Contreras Maza, Oswaldo, 2000 (Box-folder 31: 3)
    - Ciavaldini, Hectór, 2000 (Box-folder 31: 4)
    - Mandini, Roberto, 1999 (Box-folder 31: 5)
    - Chávez, Hugo, 1999 (Box-folder 31: 6)
    - Restructuring, 1997 (Box-folder 31: 7)
    - Exploration, 1997 (Box-folder 31: 8)
    - La Apertura bidding, 1996 (Box-folder 31: 9)
    - Profit sharing, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 31: 10)
    - Cuba, 2000 (Box-folder 31: 11)
    - Marginal fields, 1991-1993
      - 1991 (Box-folder 32: 1-2)
      - 1993 (Box-folder 32: 3-4)
    - Petroleum Congress, 1990 (Box-folder 32: 5)
    - Nationalization, 1975-1986 (Box-folder 32: 6)
    - Service contracts, 1971 (Box-folder 32: 7)
- Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC), 1973-2002
  - OPEC and Venezuela, 1985-2002 (Box-folder 32: 8-9)
  - General, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 32: 10)
  - History, 1973-2001 (Box-folder 33: 1)
  - Downstream ventures, 1975-1991 (Box-folder 33: 2)
- Venezuela, 1952-2004
  - Petróleos de Venezuela, 1980-2002
    - Oil storage, 1985-2000 (Box-folder 33: 3)
    - Refineries, 1980-2002 (Box-folder 33: 4-6)
    - Environmental laws, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 33: 7)
  - Pensions and severance pay, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 33: 8)
  - Caldera, Rafael, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 33: 9)
  - Velásquez, Ramón J., 1993-1994 (Box-folder 33: 10)
  - Pérez, Carlos Andrés, 1993-2002 (Box-folder 33: 11-12)
  - Cacerolazo, 1992 (Box-folder 33: 13)
  - Political upheaval, 1992 (Box-folder 33: 14)
  - Embassy in Libya, 1992 (Box-folder 33: 15)
  - General, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 34: 1)
  - Pérez, Carlos Andrés, 1974-1989
    - 1974-1979 (Box-folder 34: 2)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 34: 3-4)
  - Cacerolazo, 1992 (Box-folder 34: 5)
  - Caracas uprising, 1989 (Box-folder 34: 6)
  - Lusinchi, Jaime, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 34: 7-8)
  - Presidential elections, 1988 (Box-folder 34: 9)
  - Herrera Campíns, Luis, 1979-1990 (Box-folder 34: 10)
  - Elections, 1973 (Box-folder 34: 11)
  - Caldera, Rafael, 1969-1992 (Box-folder 34: 12)
  - Leoni, Raul, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 34: 13)
  - Politics, 1957-2000 (Box-folder 34: 14)
  - Armed forces, 1981-2002 (Box-folder 34: 15)
  - Congress, 1971-2000 (Box-folder 34: 16)
  - Supreme court, 1974-1999 (Box-folder 34: 17)
  - Regional integration, 1969-2000 (Box-folder 34: 18)
  - Pérez Jiménez, Marcos, 1952-2001 (Box-folder 35: 1-2)
  - Larrazábal, Wolfgang, 1958 (Box-folder 35: 3)
  - Betancourt, Rómulo, 1958 (Box-folder 35: 4)
  - Reports, 2002-2004 (Box-folder 35: 5)
- Speeches and writings by Brossard, 1950-2003
  - "United States Foreign Relations with Venezuela, 1776-1898,", 1950 January (Box-folder 35: 6)